Guide to the Margery Clinton Papers, 1908-1966 (bulk 1908-1910)
Archives and Special Collections Library, Vassar College Libraries
Margery Clinton Papers
1908-1966
1908-1910
Clinton, Margery
0.2 cubic feet (1 box)
Archives and Special Collections Library, Vassar College Libraries
The Margery Clinton Papers include correspondence, photographs, clippings and other materials relating to Clinton's relationship with Samuel Clemens (Mark Twain).
Biographical Note
Margery Hamilton Clinton (24 Jun 1887 - Feb 1980) was the daughter of Emily de S. Gorsuch and the well-known New York City architect Charles W. Clinton. The Clintons had homes in New York City as well as Tuxedo Park. According to a collection of Samuel Clemens letters edited by John Cooley (Mark Twain's Aquarium, Athens: University of Georgia Press, 1991), Margery Clinton met Clemens some time in 1907 or 1908 through a mutual friend, Mary Rogers, also of Tuxedo Park. The two struck up a friendship, and Clinton was invited on several occasions to Stormfield, Clemens' home in Redding, Connecticut. Visits and correspondence between the two continued through the rest of Clemens' life. His last existing letter to her was 17 November 1909, although there is an empty envelope in the collection postmarked from Bermuda, 10 February 1910. Clemens died 10 weeks later at Stormfield.
Clinton later married Lamar R. Leahy, a navy man who had served in WWI and was eventually made Rear Admiral. They had no children. She died in 1980 in New York at the age of 93.
Scope and Content Note
The Margery Clinton Papers include correspondence, photographs, clippings and other materials relating to Clinton's relationship with Samuel Clemens. The most significant items can be found in the correspondence. Although many of the letters are brief, Clemens corresponded with Clinton for at least two years. Most letters are about planned visits or requests for visits (for some reason Clinton is frequently referred to as "the plumber"), but the letters also include updates on Clemens' declining health. Other correspondents include Clemens' daughter Clara; his business manager, Ralph Ashcroft (sometimes referred to as "The Bishop" or "Benares"); and his secretary, Isabel Lyon. There are also two letters from Clinton to her father, one of which includes a description of a visit she and her friend Caroline Rogers had with President William Howard Taft. Armed only with a letter of introduction from Clemens, the two young women asked for and were granted a meeting with the newly elected president the day before his inauguration.
Access
This collection is open for research according to the regulations of the Vassar College Archives and Special Collections Library without any additional restrictions.
Related Materials
Samuel L. Clemens Papers
Subject Headings
Names:
Twain, Mark, 1835-1910; Lyon, Isabel, 1863-1958; Ashcroft, Ralph W.
Subjects:
Authors, American--20th century; Humorists, American--20th century
Document Types:
Correspondence; Clippings (information artifacts); Photographs; Printed ephemera
VCL Categories:
Literature and Writing
Encoding Information
Encoded by Laura Streett, January 2010. Updated by Emma Gronbeck, October 2025.
Acquisition Information
Gift of Mrs. Nathaniel Burt, February 1982. Mrs. Burt was probably Margaret Clinton Burt, the daughter of Clinton's brother, Charles K. Clinton.
Arrangement
At some point the scrapbook was unbound. The current arrangement does not reflect original order.
Container List
- Correspondence — Ashcroft, Ralph, 1909; (2 ALS) (Folder 1)
- Correspondence — Ashcroft, Ralph and Isabel Lyon, 1909 Mar 11; (1 ALS) (Folder 2)
- Correspondence — Clemens, Clara, 1910; (1 ALS, 1 TLS, 1 sympathy acknowledgment card) (Folder 3)
- Correspondence — Clemens, Clara, 1912, 1936; (1 ALS, 1 postcard) (Folder 4)
- Correspondence — Clemens, Samuel L., 1908; (3 ALS, 1 postcard, 1 personalized invitation to his library fundraiser) (Folder 5)
- Correspondence — Clemens, Samuel L., 1909 Feb - Mar; (3 ALS, 1 transcript of letter to President Taft) (Folder 6)
- Correspondence — Clemens, Samuel L., 1909 Aug - Nov; (4 ALS, 1 invitation) (Folder 7)
- Correspondence — Clemens, Samuel L., 1909-1910; (2 empty envelopes) (Folder 8)
- Correspondence — Clinton, Margery to her father, 1909; (1 ALS, 1 fragment) (Folder 9)
- Correspondence — Dilling, Mildred, [no year] May 2; (series of 3 postcards) (Folder 10)
- Correspondence — Lyon, Isabel, 1908; (3 ALS) (Folder 11)
- Correspondence — Lyon, Isabel, 1909; (2 ALS, 1 wedding invitation, 1 calling card) (Folder 12)
- Correspondence — Lyon, Isabel, undated; (3 ALS) (Folder 13)
- Correspondence — Lyon, Mrs. G. V., 1909; (1 ALS) (Folder 14)
- Correspondence — O'Shea, Beth, 1947 Jan 30; (1 ALS) (Folder 15)
- Miscellaneous notes and scraps relating to Clinton's experiences with Clemens, undated; (1 SLC calling card and 5 additional items) (Folder 16)
- Clemens photographs [at Stormfield], [1908?]; (2 sheets w/ 8 prints and 8 loose prints) (Folder 17)
- Stormfield guest book photocopies and related correspondence, 1936 (Folder 18)
- Mark Twain memorial, undated (Folder 19)
- "Mark Twain Tonight" material, 1959-1966, undated; (includes 2 ALS from Hal Holbrook) (Folder 20)
- Clippings, undated (Folder 21)
- Miscellaneous, undated (Folder 22)
- Original scrapbook cover, undated (Folder 23)